Guide to the Oral Histories Documenting New Haven, Connecticut
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Interviews, Accession 2008-A-001
  - Kubler, Elizabeth, 2004 February 18; computer file (WAV)
    After growing up in New Haven and attending Smith College, Elizabeth Kubler returned to New Haven to study at the Yale Art School. Kubler quickly involved herself in the arts scene in New Haven. She began her work with the Women's Auxiliary of the New Haven symphony orchestra, which provided food for the musicians and planned a number of special events. In the 1960s, Kubler was involved in the creation of the Neighborhood Music School and was a key player in the formation of Long Wharf theater, along with founders Jon Jory and Harlan Kleinman. Kubler served on the Board of Long Wharf for decades. Kubler also discusses the development of the Audubon arts district, the creation of the New Haven Arts Council, and the City Spirit Artists grant from the Federal Government, received in 1976, which created an organization to promote public art in the city. She comments on the commitment of a number of New Haven mayoral administrations to the arts since the 1960s, and suggests that New Haven's success in fostering the arts is largely due to the concerted efforts of a small group of citizens constantly pushing the city to further its commitment to art. She includes Mary Hunter Wolf and Charles Newton "Newt" Schenck in this category.
    Interviewer: Horowitz, Andy
    Length (min): 66
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Leahy, Kathleen, 2003 November 4; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Esteves, Charles
    Length (min): 80, 42
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Leavitt, Cornelia, 2004 October 29; computer file (WAV)
    Cornelia Leavitt (nee Mitchell) graduated from Hillhouse High School in 1944, one of the top students in her class. Leavitt, an African American, attended Hillhouse High School at a time when only about five per cent of the student body was African American but she asserts that race was never an issue that she paid much attention to. She has very fond memories of Hillhouse, its excellent academics, its inspiring teachers, and her close group of friends. If there was discrimination, Leavitt maintains, she was oblivious to it. Leavitt touches on ethnicity and talks about Jewish and Italian populations at the school. She also alludes to economic issues that affected some students in post-Depression New Haven. She discusses World War II and its impacts on her personally and on the community, remembering that many people she knew were killed or pronounced missing in action. The school, she says, provided a strong community network to keep people together even in times of hardship. After graduating, Leavitt attended Fisk University and the Universities of Wisconsin and Connecticut. She was among the first African American social workers in the state of Connecticut and her sister, Emma Ruff, was the first African American prinicipal of Hillhouse High School.
    Interviewer: Hertz, Allie
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Lee, Rev. David, 2003 December 15; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Rosenberg, Alyssa
    Length (min): 62
  - Lee, Timmy, 2004 November 16; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Duque, Pamela
    Length (min): 37
  - Lee, William T., 2004 October 6; computer file (WAV)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Lloyd, Marie, 2005 February 18; computer file (WAV)
    Marie Lloyd, the daughter of German immigrants, was born in New Haven and grew up in the State Street area. She recalls her memories of attending church and school at St. Boniface Church. Lloyd started school at St. Boniface in 1921 and completed eight grades. She mentions that German, Polish, Italian, and Irish individuals all attended St. Boniface. Lloyd also discusses the community that St. Boniface fostered. She attended dances there and was part of the Women's Society. After she married and moved out of the State Street area, she lived too far from the church to engage in its social activities or to send her children to school there. But she continued to attend with her family each Sunday, as did her parents, siblings, and their families. Lloyd then talks about how things in the church changed as its parishioners moved to the suburbs. She and her husband left New Haven in 1955 because they wanted better housing and better schools and believed that New Haven was "getting rough and tough." As more families left, the church began to lose members. At the time of the interview, the Archdiocese at Hartford planned to close St. Boniface because it did not have enough parishioners. Lloyd laments the loss of community that she will feel if the church closes.
    Length (min): 71
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Lopes, Matthew Jr., 2005 February 28; computer file (WAV)
    Matthew Lopes was born in New Haven, attended public schools in the city, graduated from Yale College in 1972, and went on to receive his Masters in Public Health and to complete three years of medical school at Yale. After working in Hartford for several years, Lopes returned to New Haven to run the city's AIDS Division and helped establish the city's Needle Exchange Program. The fist part of the interview describes the culture of Yale College and its professional schools in the 1970s and the increasing ethnic, class, and gender diversity of the schools under President Kingman Brewster. Lopes then talks about starting the New Haven Needle Exchange Program. Despite political opposition from conservatives in Hartford, Lopes, Elaine O'Keefe, Bill Quinn, and the Mayor's Task Force on AIDS succeeded in establishing their pilot program and received $25,000 from the State Legislature to fund it. Lopes talks about the outreach programs that he helped establish in various neighborhoods of New Haven. He also discusses the supportive political culture in New Haven from the Mayor's office and the Chief of Police. Lopes also talks about the New Haven AIDS Services Department more generally, discussing its activities in HIV counseling and testing, AIDS education outreach, and assistance in finding housing for AIDS patients. Finally, he talks about public health as a career path.
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 77U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - McDonald, Curlena, 2007 April 5; computer file (WAV)
    Curlena McDonald moved into the Dwight Street neighborhood from Newhallville in the late 1980s, just as drugs were beginning to become a large problem in the New Haven African-American community. McDonald speaks about the disappointment within the black community at that time, regarding the lack of substantive change in the years following the Civil Rights and Black Power movements. In the early 1990s, McDonald recalls, black residents of the Dwight area found themselves stuck between an influx of drug dealers and a New Haven police force that many deemed untrustworthy and dangerous. As a result, community members formed the Management Team in an attempt to arrest the spread of drugs and crime. Among other things, the Management Team provided small grants for area youths to undertake projects to clean up and beautify their neighborhoods. When the Management Team found partners in Yale and St. Rafael's Hospital, the organization morphed into the Greater Dwight Development Corporation. Among other ventures, McDonald reports, the Corporation was able to bring a Shaw's Supermarket to the Dwight area, to encourage home ownership, and to open a Montessori school and a business school. McDonald discusses the relative advantages and disadvantages of the movement from a grassroots organization to a better funded, more centralized structure. She surveys what the community activists of the Management Team have been able to accomplish, and what's left to achieve.
    Interviewer: Chilukuri, Usha
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Maier, Linda, 2007 February 16; computer file (WAV)
    Linda Maier arrived in New Haven in 1953. Her father had left the South in search of work in 1950, and brought his family to New Haven to join him three years later. Redevelopment forced the family from their home on Canal Street. In 1989, she got involved in community activism, working on neighborhood watches and beautification in the Dwight Street area. She describes a number of community initiatives to combat gangs, drugs, and crime, including a "John of the Week" program, which attempted to discourage prostitution in the Dwight area by publicly embarrassing men purchasing sex, and a garden project and environmental awareness program for children in the neighborhood. Maier was also a leader in the Management Team, which instituted community policing in the Dwight area in the early 1990s, and continues its work today. Maier discusses the efforts of the Management Team and its sister organization, the Greater Dwight Development Corporation, in bringing a supermarket to the Dwight area, opening a Montessori school, and developing an effective home-buyer assistance program. She promises more housing for the elderly and better rental properties in the Dwight area in the future. Maier served briefly as an alderwoman, but reports that the process left her disappointed. Maier also discusses the relationship between Yale and the community.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Mailhouse, Robert, 2004 December 3; computer file (WAV)
    Robert Mailhouse grew up in the East Rock neighborhood of New Haven and attended Hillhouse High School from 1936 until 1940. The interview focuses primarily on his experiences during that period. Mailhouse's father, a Yale graduate and electrical engineer, started the Plymouth Electric Company in New Haven. Mailhouse says that his family was not terribly hard hit by the Great Depression but that they moved in with his grandparents to save money. He talks about Hillhouse High School's wonderful academic reputation, its good teachers, and its success at preparing him for college. He enjoyed many social activities there, particularly athletics, and was a member of one of the high school fraternities. Prompted by the interviewer, Mailhouse spends a good deal of time discussing the African American students at the school. He recalls that African American students made up only a small percentage of the class. He did not perceive much overt racism towards them but remembers that African American and white students did not generally socialize that much. He believes that this was voluntary on both parts and that students did not give it much thought. After graduating from Hillhouse, Mailhouse attended Colorado College. He talks about his time there and compares high school with college.
    Interviewer: Allison Hertz
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Maldonado, Dominick, 2005 March 14; computer file (WAV)
    Dominick Maldonado was born in Puerto Rico but grew up in Fair Haven. After graduating from Wilbur Cross High School, he joined the Air Force then returned to New Haven and worked with substance abusers at Crossroads, Inc., a residential treatment facility. In the 1980s, he began work in HIV/AIDS outreach, education, and prevention. Maldonado recalls growing up as a Puerto Rican in New Haven and the discrimination he faced. Most of the interview focuses on his work in HIV/AIDS in the Latino community and with the Needle Exchange Program. In the early 1980s, Maldonado states, there was little HIV/AIDS information available except for members of the homosexual Anglo community. Maldonado created Hispanos Unidos to reach out to the Latino community and to confront its cultural taboos about HIV/AIDS. He was also one of the first three members of a community outreach team that worked with addicts in the New Haven community to educate them about HIV and intravenous drug use. In 1987, Maldonado, Sher Horosko, and Elaine O'Keefe, came up with the idea of a Needle Exchange Program as a way to move beyond education. In 1990, they received a $25,000 grant from the Connecticut State Legislature to start a pilot program in New Haven. Yale Researchers Edward Kaplan and Bob Heimer secured $250,000 in services from Yale and a van from the university for the program. Maldonado remarks that this assistance and the support of Police Chief Nicholas Pastore helped make the Needle Exchange Program a national model.
    - Use copy, compact disc (Audio CD) (Box 81U)
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Margolis, Leonard, 2003 November 28; computer file (WAV)
    Interviewer: Reeve, Alexandra
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Melnyk, Christine, 2006 April 12; computer file (WAV)
    Christine Melnyk immigrated to New Haven with her family in 1949 and joined the city's sizeable Ukranian American population. Melnyk discusses the Ukranian American community and her involvement with it as a child and an adult. Her family arrived as part of a second wave of Ukranian immigrants fleeing Russian political control, an influx that peaked during the 1950s. Melynk's family lived near the Ukranian Church that was on Park Street and spent much time there. She also joined Platzt, a Ukranian society, went to Ukranian school three times a week, and joined the Ukranian National Women's League of America after college. Her family spoke Ukranian in the home, and Melnyk's own daughters learnd Ukranian before English. She talks about her identification with two cultures, American and Ukranian. She also discusses her efforts to preserve and promote Ukranian culture as an adult, through activities in various societies, annual community celebrations, and through outreach at the Ethnic Heritage Center at Southern Connectitcut State University. She worries that the newer Ukranian immigrants have less interest in their cultural heritage than did the members of her generation and discusses her fear that the community has become somewhat stagnant.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Mielcarz, Karen, 2007 April 29; computer file (WAV)
    Karen Mielcarz first started visiting downtown New Haven in the late 1970s while she was a student at the Paier School of Art in Hamden. Since that time she rented housing in the Newhallville neighborhood, on Chapel Street, and in Hamden and then bought a home in Fair Haven in the early 2000s. She recalls how much she enjoyed being a young person in New Haven in the late 1970s and early 1980s and talks about going to shows at Toad's Place, the Agora Theater, the Grotto, and at the Coliseum and about patronizing small businesses and restaurants like Blessings, Group W Bench, and Dava. She also remembers working at print shops on State Street. In the early 1990s she married but divorced several years later. When she remarried in 2001, she and her husband bought a home in Fair Haven because it was beautiful and affordable and they were tired of being tenants. However, she explains that crime and high costs have made being a landlord more difficult than she realized it would be. Mielcarz misses some of the things that she believed made New Haven unique in the 1970s and 1980s. Though she enjoys the arts culture and restaurants of present-day New Haven, she feels that it is unaffordable. She also laments that crime has made her neighborhood a difficult place to live.
    Interviewer: Cannell, Oliver
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Miller, Mary, 2005 March 25; computer file (WAV)
    Mary Miller was the Festival Director of the International Festival of Arts and Ideas from 2001 until 2005. Miller spent her childhood in Edinburgh, Scotland, where she began playing the violin at the age of three. As an adult, she had a career in the orchestra before becoming a music critic. Later she became the festival director for the United Kingdom's festival of Nordic Culture and organized community outreach programs for the English National Opera. In 2001, she received an invitation to take over New Haven's International Festival of Arts and Ideas. Miller admits that she had not planned to move to the United States, but was intrigued by New Haven's international population and its interest in culture and arts. Miller spends much of the interview discussing her philosophical approach to the Festival. She sees it, and art more generally, as a means to encourage social cohesion and bring different parts of the New Haven community together. Ethnic, national, and cultural differences can be bridged through the arts, Miller suggests. She also discusses attempts to involve children in the arts. Later, she discusses funding difficulties and the Festival's attempts to collaborate with other local organizations, including Yale University, the Dixwell neighborhood's gospel festival, and the Long Wharf, Shubert, and Yale Reperatory Theaters.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Milvojevic, Kovilka and Verica, 2007 April 7
    Kovilka Milvojevic and her daughter, Verica, fled Bosnia in 1992 and spent several years in Germany before coming to New Haven in 2000 through the help of the Interfaith Ministry Refuge. The two women discuss their experiences as refugees and the home that they purchased in the Chatham Square area of Fair Haven. The two Milvojevics remember coming to the United States with only two suitcases each and discuss their first few years in New Haven. They lived in a Westville apartment initially but Verica moved to attend Albertus Magnus University several months after they arrived. Kovilka talks about her language difficulties but says that the Interfaith Ministry Refuge and her employer, Yale University, helped her become established in Connecticut. The two discuss the differences that they perceive between the United States and Bosnia. They appreciate the freedom of religion and speech but believe that many Americans are unaware of international events and drive their cars too much. With a grant for low-income families and assistance from the Yale Homebuyer Program, Kovilka bought a home in Chatham Square. The two talk about how much they enjoy the neighborhood and their efforts to improve it through block watch programs and other community uplift programs.
    Interviewer: Marcus, Jacob
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Morand, Michael, 2004 April 16; 2005 April 8; 2 separate audio interview recordings.
    After graduating from Yale College in 1987 and Yale Divinity School in 1993, Michael Morand began his career working for the Yale University Office of New Haven and State Affairs. Morand describes the work of this Office in encouraging New Haven's economic development. This office was established in 1995, two years after Richard Levin became president, as a way to connect Yale to the community and to look for ways to make the city attractive to investors and businesses. He discusses community development and public relations initiatives such as the Yale Homebuyer Program, the Yale Entrepreneurial Society, and Market New Haven. He also recounts efforts to increase flights to Tweed-New Haven Airport and to encourage biotechnology and venture capital initiatives in the city. Morand spends much of the interview touting the benefits of New Haven, to both residents and businesses, and comparing it to other towns. He also contrasts New Haven's current development plan of "strategic incrementalism" to the larger-scale urban renewal and Model City efforts of the 1950s and 1960s.
    Interviewer: Eidelson, Josh
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Murray, Marian, 2003 November 14; computer file (WAV)
  - Naddis, Daniel, 2007 April 26; computer file (WAV)
    Daniel Naddis moved to Connecticut for work in 1982 and chose to live in New Haven because of its Jewish community resources, including a synagogue, Jewish school, and the availability of Kosher provisions. Most of his interview talks about the changing availability of Kosher food and its effects on the community. Naddis emphasizes that patronizing local businesses, such as bakers and butchers, is a way to nurture community and communal institutions. Yet cost, convenience, quality, and increasing strictness of Kosher standards have made it difficult for small businesses to compete with larger supermarkets, especially Stop and Shop. Naddis is involved with the Kosher Advocacy Group, which urges unity among the Jewish community by trying to reach consensus on Kosher regulations. In addition to Kosher food, Naddis talks about day schools and other educational opportunities for New Haven Jews. He also compares New Haven's Jewish community with London, England, where he used to live.
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Nash, Lola, 2006 April 12; computer file (WAV)
    Lola Nash set up the first Head Start Program in the United States in the Elm Haven neighborhood of New Haven. She was also one of the founders of the Edith B. Jackson family daycare center in New Haven and, in the 1980s, established a daycare at Yale New Haven Hospital to provide child care to nurses and other female employees. Before coming to New Haven, Nash cultivated a background in early childhood education by working in many diverse programs. She graduated from college in 1945 then worked for government-sponsored day care centers in New York City, a wartime program to allow mothers to labor in factories and other industries. She then traveled to Burma with her husband and home-schooled their children while teaching music to local children. After returning to the United States, she taught at public schools serving low-income communities in New York. She and her husband moved to New Haven in the 1960s because he was hired to set up alternative school programs. Nash was then asked to establish the Head Start program, which was funded as a pilot program and further supported by Ed Ziegler and the Yale Child Studies Center. She talks about her experiences there, her teaching philosophies, and Head Start's commitment to physical and emotional needs of children and their parents.
    Interviewer: Sauer, Jordan
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - Nasti, Frank, Jr., 2003 December 4; computer file (WAV)
    The son of Italian immigrants, Frank Nasti, Jr. grew up in Fair Haven and became involved in redevelopment projects there in the late 1960s. In 1968, Nasti became president of the Fair Haven Project Area Committee, a group of local residents who made recommendations to the New Haven Redevelopment Agency about urban renewal initiatives. Nasti and other members of the Committee lobbied to change New Haven's demolition plans and instead pushed for the construction of single- and two-family homes. He helped raise money for their construction and secured building permits. As President of the Corporation for Urban Home Ownership, a non-profit development corporation, Nasti worked to construct of affordable urban housing for purchase and rental throughout the 1970s and 1980s. Most of the interview focuses on his experiences in these endeavors. Nasti criticizes Richard Lee's urban renewal efforts for being out of touch with local needs and desires. He also talks about the demographic shift in Fair Haven from Italian and Irish to Latino populations and the decline of industrial and manufacturing jobs.
    Interviewer: Sánchez, Christina
    Length (min): 54
    - Transcript, computer file (DOC)
  - O'Connell, Craig, 2003 July 2; computer file (WAV)